A Guide to the Adèle Goodman Clark papers, 1849-1978
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Series IV: Richmond League of Women Voters, 1920- 1978
Series V: Virginia League of Women Voters, 1915-1967
Subseries A: President/Executive Secretary Correspondence, 1920-1944
Subseries B: Board of Directors/Executive Committee/General Council/Standing/Special Committees File, 1921-1934
Subseries C: State/National League Convention Material, 1921-1933
Subseries D: Financial Material, 1921-1939
Subseries E: Legislative Material, 1921-1944
Subseries F: Local District/League Material, 1920-1934
Subseries G: University of Virginia File--University Extension Division, 1920-1938
Subseries H: Other Organizations, 1915-1956
Subseries I: Governor's Ball, 1926-1929
Subseries J: Virginia Cookery Book, 1921-1937
Subseries K: Topical File, 1918-1967
Series VI: League of Women Voters of Virginia, 1945-1970
Series VII: National League of Women Voters, 1919-1947
Subseries A: Adèle Clark Officer File, 1924-1932
Subseries B: Standing Committees\Departments File, 1919- 1935
Subseries C: Topical File, 1919-1947
Series VIII: League of Women Voters, 1946-1976
Series IX: Commission on Simplification of State and Local Government, 1921-1927
Series X: Liberal Arts College for Women Commission, 1918-1970
Series XI: The National Reemployment Service, 1925-1938
Series XII: Lila Meade Valentine Memorial Association, 1921-1936
Series XIII: Religious Materials, 1893-1970
Subseries A: Richmond Diocesan Council of Catholic Women (RDCCW), 1948-1970
Subseries B: Literature, 1922-1970
Subseries C: Organizational Correspondence, 1912-1970
Subseries D: Topical File, 1893-1970
Series XIV: Art, 1850-1971
Subseries A: Art Club of Richmond, 1895-1919
Subseries B: Atelier, 1918-1937 [merged with the restored Academy in the spring of 1930]
Subseries C: Virginia League of Fine Arts and Handicrafts, 1919-1934 [grew out of the Atelier and later merged with the Academy]
Subseries D: Richmond Academy of Arts/Academy of Sciences and Fine Arts, 1917-1953
Subseries E: Virginia Arts Commission [established 1916], 1913-1965
Subseries F: Works Project Administration/Virginia Arts Project, 1935-1942
Subseries G: Other Art Organizations, 1932-1971
Subseries H: Printed Materials, 1901- 1969
Subseries I: Topical File, 1917-1968
Subseries J: Artwork, 1850-1939
Series XV: Ephemera and Photographs, 1850s-1970s
Subseries A: Newspaper Clippings, 1910s-1970s
Subseries B: Ephemera, 1918-1950
Subseries C: Photographs, 1850s-1970s
Series I: Correspondence and Family Materials, 1849-1971, has been organized into four major subseries.
Subseries A consists of the personal correspondence, diaries, poetry, short stories, memoranda, notes written by Adèle Clark, as well as legal and real estate data pertaining to Clark's residence at 3614 Chamberlayne Ave. Clark's written manuscript entitled "My Cossack" is included. The subseries has been further divided by family members, friends and associates and outgoing and miscellaneous correspondence only roughly identified. Correspondence found in this subseries provides some biographical data on several members of the Clark family and close personal friends.
Subseries B consists of all of the correspondence written to the members of the Clark family (Cowles, Ions and Goodman families) and personal items. Arranged alphabetically, some of the letters are addressed to more than one individual, legal and real estate data of property owned by the members of these families.
Subseries C includes correspondence written to Nora Houston, her mother, Mrs. Josephine Dooley Houston, and other members of the family, personal items of the Dooley-Houston family legal and real estate data. The materials have been arranged in a similar fashion to that found in Subseries A. This section provides detailed information about Alice Dooley, Coralie Floyd Lewis, Florence Dooley Lewis and Sarah Lewis Woodville.
Subseries D consists of the correspondence, essays, poetry and items from individuals not obviously related to the Clark or Houston families.
Subseries E consists of birthday, Christmas, holiday, sympathy cards and commencement, wedding and other invitations received by Adèle Clark. Most of the material is arranged according to type. Some of Clark's Christmas cards are arranged chronologically.
Series II: Business/Civic Organization Correspondence, 1903-1971, has been organized into three major subseries.
Subseries A consists of correspondence from various business and civic organizations with which Adèle was affiliated during her life. Various local civic associations are represented including the Richmond Child Labor Committee, Richmond Council on Adult Education and Richmond Public Forum. There is also correspondence from several state, civic and government entities such as the Virginia Women's Council of Legislative Chairman of State Organizations. In the Virginia Society for Crippled Children and Handicapped Adults file, there is correspondence between Adèle and Cornelia Adair, President of the Richmond Area Chapter and Walter C. Chapman, Executive Director of the Virginia Society in regards to program and fundraising events put on by the society. This file also documents Clark's teaching of art and drawing to the children who were cared for by the society. Clark also corresponded with several national organizations devoted to social and political reforms such as the Woodrow Wilson Foundation, National Consumers League and Social Science Research Council-Committee on Public Administration. In the Woodrow Wilson Foundation file there is one letter addressed to Adèle Clark from Franklin D. Roosevelt, who thanked her for contributing money to the foundation. As a result of Clark's political activities in Virginia there are a number of letters from prominent members of both the executive and legislative branches of state government, including Harry F. Byrd, Jr., E. Lee Trinkle and Hill Montague.
Subseries B consists of the business correspondence of Adèle's sister, Edith Clark Cowles. Included in this small subseries is correspondence from the Richmond Training School where Mrs. Cowles taught for a number of years.
Subseries C contains all of the correspondence to Nora Houston, Mrs. Josephine Houston, and Alice Dooley from business and civic organizations and prominent local and state civic leaders. Arranged alphabetically, most of the correspondence is addressed to Nora Houston during the period when she was most active in civic affairs. Some of the local civic organizations in which Houston was active include the Business and Professional Women's Club of Richmond, City Democratic Committee, Richmond Community Fund, Richmond Tuberculosis Association, and Commission on Inter-Racial Cooperation.
Series III: Equal Suffrage League of Virginia (ESLV), 1892-1926, is composed of eight major subseries.
Subseries A contains the correspondence of the President/Secretary and is arranged chronologically. This subseries includes incoming and outgoing correspondence of the main office of the ESLV, a large portion generated by the corresponding secretaries. Significant correspondence within the series is addressed to President Lila M. Valentine from prominent members of the national suffrage movement, such as letters from Kate Gordon, President of the Southern States Woman Suffrage Conference and Carrie Chapman Catt regarding the plank proposed by the National American Woman Suffrage Association in 1916.
Subseries B Equal Suffrage League of Richmond consists of bulletins and circulars, drafts, notes and correspondence of the Board of Directors/Executive Committee, as well as lists of officers and members of the local League. Arranged alphabetically much of the material from the local suffrage league covers only the last two years of its existence.
Subseries C National American Woman Suffrage Association consists primarily of literature and is arranged alphabetically. This includes the "Efficiency Booklet Series" pamphlets, political equality leaflets, convention brochures, and press releases.
Subseries D contains literature distributed by state and national suffrage organizations. The series also contains other organizational materials devoted to reform. Three organizations of particular note are the Empire State Campaign Committee 1914-1915/New York State Woman Suffrage Party 1916-1917, Just Government League of Maryland, and Southern States Woman Suffrage Conference.
Subseries E comprises a wide range of materials pertaining to the activities of the ESLV and is arranged alphabetically. There are more than a dozen essays written by such Virginia activists as Kate Langley Bosher, Adèle Clark, and Lucy R. Mason. Also included is printed literature documenting the anti-suffrage movement.
Subseries F consists of signed enrollment cards.
Subseries G includes signed petitions of the ESLV that are arranged alphabetically by county and city.
Subseries H consists of petitions to the Virginia General Assembly and is also arranged alphabetically by county and city. Petitions include information on an individual's occupation in addition to name and address.
Series IV: The Richmond League of Women Voters, undated, 1920-1978, has been arranged in two different ways. The President/Executive Secretary Correspondence has been arranged chronologically. The remainder of the series has been arranged alphabetically by subject and record type.
Series V: Virginia League of Women Voters (VLWV), 1915-1967, has been organized into twelve major subseries.
Subseries A is arranged chronologically and consists of all of the correspondence from various officers of the National League of Women Voters. The NLWV officers include the President, Congressional Executive, Press secretary, various chairpersons from the NLWV standing committees, the treasurer and assistant treasurer, and the vice-presidents. The large amount of correspondence between the state and national office provides valuable insight into the legislative reform agenda of the NLWV during the first two decades of its existence. It also provides information on the amount and breakdown of dues the VLWV was expected to pay on an annual basis. In addition to the correspondence of the NLWV, there is also a considerable quantity of outside correspondence from civic organizations involved in legislative reforms. For example, the Florence Crittenton Mission, Co-Operative Education Association, American Social Hygiene Association and National Popular Government League lobbied the VLWV to support specific bills before Congress. Edith Clark Cowles held the post of executive secretary of the VLWV from 1920 to 1922 and Ida Mae Thompson was executive secretary of the VLWV from 1922-1934. This series includes correspondence from significant VLWV members such as Mrs. C.E. "Jessie" Townsend, Roberta Wellford, Mary Elizabeth Pidgeon, Jeffries Heinrich, Mrs. John L. Lewis and Kate Waller Barrett. After 1933, the correspondence in the subseries reflects Clark's increasing interest in issues related to labor and unemployment. Letters form Secretary of Labor Frances Perkins and the Assistant Director of the Division of Labor Standards, Clara M. Beyer, pertain to state and federal labor legislation advocated by the Department of Labor. Little specific information is provided on the actual reorganization of VLWV because of gaps in the correspondence during this time period.
Subseries B consists of records generated by the Board of Director, Executive Committee, General Council and major standing committees of the VLWV. The minutes of the Executive Committee and the Board of Directors document in great detail actions taken by various standing committees on proposed programs. The committee portion of the subseries is arranged alphabetically by committee name. The work of the nine standing committees parallels that of the standing committees and departments of the NLWV.
Subseries C is comprised of materials pertaining to the participation of Adèle Clark and other VLWV members in the state and national league conventions. Arranged chronologically by year, the records of the national convention primarily consist of the correspondence of VLWV members who attended the conventions. There is, however, additional material in the files of the 1925 NLWV Richmond convention such as program committee correspondence, staff conference minutes and notes and Gala Finance Luncheon data. These files demonstrate the time and effort that Clark and others put into planning the national convention held in Richmond.
Subseries D consists of material created by the Finance Department and the Treasurer's Office of the VLWV. The treasurer of the state league established quotas for local leagues, while the finance chairperson's main duty was to devise the means for raising money in the VLWV.
Subseries E contains materials pertaining to the activities of the Children's Code Commission, Virginia Women's Council of Legislative Chairman of State Organizations, and the legislative committee of the VLWV. New state and federal legislation concerning child welfare, health and education, economy and efficiency in government and the legal status of women were closely monitored by the VLWV's legislative chairperson. Nora Houston, who served as the VLWV legislative chair for six years, corresponded regularly with the sponsors of key pieces of legislation originating in the Virginia General Assembly. The file of candidates/legislator's replies, as well as other materials, in this subseries documents the successes and failures of the VLWV advocacy of key legislative measures.
Subseries F documents the formation and activities of local leagues throughout Virginia. The original order (alphabetical by city, by city/county and by county) has been maintained. While a majority of these leagues existed for only a few years, there were several that maintained a large, active group of members for more than a decade. Correspondence and reports from Mrs. C.E. [Jessie] Townsend of the Norfolk League, Mrs. John H. Lewis of the Lynchburg league and Gertrude Boatwright of the Roanoke league illustrate the successful measures these women employed in making the local organization active branches of the VLWV.
Subseries G is comprised of material relating to the VLWV's involvement in citizenship courses taught at the University of Virginia's Extension Division in providing courses that were designed to educate the new women voters on the complexities of government. Letters between Clark and citizenship course instructors, E. Jeffries Heinrich and Mary Elizabeth Pidgeon, as well as the Extension Division Director, make up the more significant correspondence in the subseries. Additional correspondence between these individuals can be found in Subseries A (President/Executive Secretary Correspondence).
Subseries H consists of a wide variety of literature from local, state, national and international civic organizations. The subseries is arranged alphabetically. Some of the more significant publications collected include the Foreign Policy Association, League of Nations [Non-Partisan] Association, National Council for the Prevention of War, and National Women's Trade Union League. The NLWV also collected literature from such state agencies as the Board of Health, Bureau/Department of Labor and Industry and Board/Department of Public Welfare. Bulletins and Publications from the U.S. Department of Labor Women's/Children's Bureau and the U.S. Civil Service Commission are also found in this subseries.
Subseries I consists of all records relating to the VLWV's short-lived fundraising activity, the Governor's Ball.
Subseries J is comprised of material pertaining to the publication and distribution of the Virginia Cookery Book. The cookbook was also a fundraising effort on the part of the VLWV.
Subseries K is arranged alphabetically and some of the more significant files in this subseries include correspondence to the congressional district directors, vice-presidents of the VLWV and between the third regional director and the VLWV. Biographical data on prominent legislators, government officials and prominent women affiliated with the VLWV can also be found in this subseries.
Series VI: The League of Women Voters of Virginia, 1945-1970, is comprised of material pertaining to the state league after its reorganization in the mid- 1940s. Although Adèle Clark was a member of the new state league, she did not serve as an officer during the later period. The series does contain, in addition to the usual materials, a convention message made by Clark in 1969 as well as scripts of local radio addresses she gave in the 1950s.
Series VII: The National League of Women Voters, 1919-1947 has been organized into three major subseries.
Subseries A: consists of materials that document Clark's major activities as a NLWV officer. Some of the more significant material in this subseries include correspondence between Clark and other NLWV officers during her tenure as third regional director (1924-1925) and as second vice president in Charge of Legislation and Law Enforcement (1925-1928). There is no correspondence between Clark and the state league in these files. Also to be found in this series is material relating to Clark's participation as a delegate to several NLWV conventions, as well as her NLWV sponsored speaking tours to different regions of the country.
Subseries B in conjunction with the usual files, contains memoranda and publications from several of the special NLWV committees: the Get-Out-the-Vote Committee, Special Committee on Immigration and Radio Committee. The voluminous amount of Committee/Department records in this subseries documents all the major spheres of legislative action and lobbying undertaken by the NLWV at this time.
Subseries C is arranged alphabetically.
Series VIII: League of Women Voters, 1946-1976, is comprised of materials related to the activities of the national league after World War II. The first part of the series, arranged alphabetically, includes some of the major surviving publications of the LWV, such as Action, Brief for Action and The National Voter.
Series IX: Commission on Simplification of State and Local Government (1921- 1927), consists of material documenting the work of the Commission charged to produce a report for the Virginia General Assembly outlining the ways in which state and local government bureaucracy could be streamlined.
Series X: Liberal Arts College for Women Commission (1918-1938) is composed of materials documenting the efforts of the Commission to establish a separate liberal arts college for women. Over a four year period, this nine member commission studied several possible sits for the new college. Some of the more significant material in this series includes correspondence between Clark, members of the Commission and city government officials whose cities were considered as proposed sites. In 1930, the Virginia General Assembly passed legislation continuing the work of the commission with the proviso that the new college be located no less that thirty miles from the University of Virginia.
Series XI: National Reemployment Service (1925-1938), is arranged alphabetically. The series contains correspondence between Clark and the State Reemployment Director, George Grey (1933-1934), and Frank Cavedo (1934-1935), correspondence and minutes from the Employment Planning Committee, literature from the U.S. Employment Services, NRS, Department of Labor and Richmond's Public Employment Bureau. Records generated by Clark and other NRS field staff demonstrate how the NRS helped local communities alleviate the critical problem of unemployment.
Series XII: Lila Meade Valentine memorial Association, 1921-1936, contains the records documenting the work of Clark and others to finance a tablet in memory of the famous suffrage leader.
Series XIII: Religious Materials has been organized into four major subseries.
Subseries A consists of materials concerning the Richmond Diocesan Council of Catholic Women. This socially active organization was an affiliate of the National Council of Catholic Women.
Subseries B is comprised of periodicals, leaflets, pamphlets and prayer books from a number of denominations. The Catholic periodicals are alphabetically arranged by title. The last five folders in this subseries consist of miscellaneous church literature.
Subseries C consists of two major parts: correspondence between Adèle Clark and local and national religious organizations with which she was affiliated and secondly, correspondence between Nora Houston and numerous Roman Catholic churches and organizations. The first is arranged alphabetically, and includes the Catholic Daughters of America, Daughters of the King, National Conference of Christians and Jews, and Richmond Diocese. The latter, also arranged alphabetically, contains correspondence from the National Council of Catholic Women, St. Joan's Social and Political Alliance, and Catholic Women's Club (Houston briefly served as president).
Subseries D contains items of a religious nature, primarily baptismal and confirmation certificates, religious essays and stories pertaining to the Roman Catholic church.
Series XIV: Art, 1850-1971, has been arranged into ten major subseries. The first six subseries contain the records of six major art organizations.
Subseries A consists of materials that document the twenty-six year history of the Art Club of Richmond, 1895-1919. The correspondence files are arranged chronologically and provide information on the relationship between the Art Club and the American Federation of Arts. It also includes information pertaining to the sale of Liberty Loan Bonds for the purpose of resurrecting the old Arts Academy.
Subseries B contains information concerning the management of the Atelier, 1918-1937.
Subseries C details Clark and Houston's work as artistic directors for the Virginia League of Fine Arts and Handicrafts (1919-1931). Since this organization was an outgrowth of the Atelier, the correspondence overlaps with the correspondence in the previous subseries.
Subseries D is comprised of material documenting the establishment and activities of the Richmond Academy of Arts/Academy of Sciences and Fine Arts (1917-1920, 1925-1944, 1946, 1949-1950). The files reveal Clark's role in the early history of the institution and her activities while serving on the Academy's Board of Trustees. There are also a number of historic accounts written by Clark on the founding of the original Arts Academy in 1786.
Subseries E contains materials spanning the twenty three period, 1941-1964, when Clark was an active member of the commission. The files contain early records of the committee to establish an Art Commission.
Subseries F consists of material concerning Clark's role as the director of the Works Project Administration--Virginia Arts Project. Under Clark's supervision, art galleries were operated in three localities and county museums in two locations, with extension work in several Virginia counties. Information concerning the art galleries and museums can be found in the narrative and monthly progress reports which Clark wrote as a WPA director. Correspondence exists discussing the establishment of the Southwest Virginia Museum at Big Stone Gap and additional material in the subseries pertains to Clark's work on the Index of American Design. Correspondence between Clark and C.A. Glasgold, the coordinator for the Index of American Design and Nora Houston, its state supervisor, demonstrates how the documentation was carried out.
Subseries G consists of information on a variety of local and state cultural institutions with which Clark was associated, including the Richmond Artists Association, Virginia Art Alliance and Virginia Museum of Fine Arts.
Subseries H contains a variety of printed materials pertaining to art work and art in general.